Vietnam Subject Files, Inclusive: 1968 — 2002, undated, Bulk: 1975 — 1990
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Vietnam Subject Files
Inclusive: 1968 — 2002, undated, Bulk: 1975 — 1990
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
10
Keston Institute, 1969 -
5 A4 document boxes
The Vietnam Subject Files contain a variety of materials on religion, government, and emigration.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the name changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist and totalitarian countries. The Keston Archive and Library houses numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
Keston collected documents dated from 1968 to 2002 reflecting the political and religious climate in Vietnam.
China ruled Vietnam from the 3rd century BC until the 10th century AD. After a prolonged period of independence, Vietnam fell under French imperial control in the nineteenth century but regained independence in the First Indochina War (1941—1954).
Although independent, Vietnam experienced political interference from Western nations, especially the United States, over matters such as elections, land reform, and social reform. Ultimately in 1965, a Western-approved government under Ngo Dinh Diem was ousted and replaced by a military régime. Internal fighting, especially against growing Viet Cong forces, became known as the Second Indochina War. Due to mounting global tensions between democracy and Communism, the U.S. entered the conflict, resulting in the Vietnam War.
Saigon, Vietnam’s most populated city, “fell” in 1975 to Communist forces and was renamed Ho Chi Minh City after the nation’s Communist leader. Religious repression became increasingly evident. The government restricted worship in an effort to diminish time spent on activities outside the Communist agenda. The edict created tension between the Vietnamese government and religious groups, including Buddhists and Roman Catholics.
Additionally, a mass emigration movement from Vietnam occurred following the War and lasted until the mid-1980’s. Many citizens fled or attempted to flee. They were sometimes referred to as “boat people” because of their escape on boats. The journeys were incredibly dangerous, often resulting in mass casualties or repatriation to Vietnam.
Vietnam continues as a one-party Communist state.
Scope and Content
The Vietnam subject files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, background briefs, emails, and newsletters and pamphlets.
The collection covers the period from 1968 to 2002 with the bulk from 1975 to1990. The majority pertain to religion, government, and emigration. Religious materials span numerous denominations, but most concern the Catholic Church following the Fall of Saigon in 1975. Topics related to the government include the Fall of Saigon, party divisions, corruption, and policies. Emigration contains items about “boat people” and other displaced Vietnamese as well as information about repatriation and reception abroad.
General Vietnam subject files contain material on history, government, oppressive practices, political prisoners, international relations, emigration, communism, tourism, literature and culture.
Vietnam’s denominational subject files include categories pertaining to specific denominations. These include Seventh Day Adventists, Baptists, Buddhists, Episcopalians, Evangelicals/General Protestants, Jewish communities, Mennonites, Muslims, Roman Catholics, and Quakers.
Arrangement
The Keston center received the Vietnam materials organized into the categories of Vietnam General Files and Vietnam Religious Files. Within these categories, all materials were organized chronologically. This organization has mostly been preserved but has been divided further into specific thematic subjects and denominations.
The Vietnam Subject Files are currently arranged in two series: I. General and II. Denominational materials.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 10.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Catholic Church -- Vietnam.; Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.
Places
Vietnam -- Emigration and immigration.; Vietnam -- History -- 1945-1975.; Vietnam -- History -- 1975-; Vietnam -- Politics and government -- 1945-1975.; Vietnam -- Politics and government -- 1975-
Subjects
Baptists -- Vietnam.; Boat people -- Vietnam.; Buddhists -- Vietnam.; Christians -- Vietnam.; Church and state -- Vietnam.; Communism -- Vietnam.; Communism and Christianity -- Vietnam.; Dissenters -- Violence against -- Vietnam.; Episcopalians -- Vietnam.; Evangelicalism -- Vietnam.; Freedom of religion -- Vietnam.; Human rights -- Vietnam.; Jews -- Vietnam.; Mennonites -- Vietnam.; Muslims -- Vietnam.; Newsletters.; Persecution -- Vietnam.; Political prisoners -- Vietnam.; Quakers -- Vietnam.; Refugees -- Vietnam.; Religion and State -- Vietnam.; Seventh-Day Adventists -- Vietnam.; Society of Friends -- Vietnam.; Vietnam -- Foreign relations -- Cambodia.; Vietnam -- History -- 20th century.; Vietnam -- Religious life and customs.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.)
- General, 1966 — 2001, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  General Vietnam subject files contain material on history, government, oppressive practices, political prisoners, international relations, emigration, communism, tourism, literature and culture.
  - General, 1975 - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Individuals, 1975 - 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - State. Government. Nationhood, 1969 - 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Elections, 1977 - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Military Affairs. Defense, 1976 - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Conscientious Objection, 1976 -1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Espionage, 1983 -1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Emigration, 1975 - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Emigration, 1981 - 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Constitution, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Basic Rights, 1977 - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Prisons. Labor Camps. Amnesty, 1977 - 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oppressive Practices, 1975 - 1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Trials, 1976 - 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Imprisonment. General, 1976 - 1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Imprisonment. Individual, 1977 - 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Expulsion of Nationals, 1976 - 1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - State Interference in Church Affairs, 1982 - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - International Relations, 1969 - 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Western Reactions, 1969 - 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - International Incidents. Hijacking. Kidnapping, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - UN and UN Specialized Agencies, 1975 - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Amnesty International, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Defense of Rights of Invalids, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Defections, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - General Interdenominational, 1966 - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - World Council of Churches, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bible, 1976 - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Conversion, 1977 - 1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Religion and Peace, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Religion Abroad, 1977 - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Oppressive Practices Related to Church Activities, 1968 - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Imprisonment of Believers, 1976 - 1993 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Religious Revivals, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Religious Minorities. Religious Sects, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Religion Statistics, 1986 - 1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Atheism, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Ideology. Communism. Propaganda. Philosophy. Morality. Ethics, 1978 - 1997 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Purges. Ideological Deviations from Party Line, 1982 - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Communism. Socialism. General, 1976 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Christianity and Communism, 1976 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Eurocommunists, 1981 - 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Agriculture, 1972 - 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Economy, 1977 - 1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Education, 1976 - 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Natural Disasters, 1977 - 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Health, 1977 - 1998 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Tourism, 1977 - 1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Television, 1975 - 1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Journalists, 1975 - 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Culture, 1982 - 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Cinema, 1984 - 1988 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - International Cultural Exchanges, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Literature, 1975 - 1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Everyday Life, 1977 - 1996 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Social Problems, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Prostitution, 1977 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Visual Materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Denominational, 1965 — 2002, undated; 2
  Vietnam’s denominational subject files include categories pertaining to specific denominations. These include Seventh Day Adventists, Baptists, Buddhists, Episcopalians, Evangelicals/General Protestants, Jewish communities, Mennonites, Muslims, Roman Catholics, and Quakers.
  - Adventist Church Life, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Baptist Church Clergy Statistics, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Buddhism. General, 1965 - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Buddhism. Church-State Relations, 1975 - 2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Buddhism. Oppressive Practices Related to Religious Activity, 1977 - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Buddhism. Imprisonment, 1975 - 1995 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Buddhism. State Expropriation, Desecration, and Demolition of Church Buildings, 1978 - 1983 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Buddhism. Ordination. Election. Retirement. Deaths, 1984 - 1997 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Buddhist Clergy, 1983 - 2000 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Buddhism. Western Reactions, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Buddhism. Public Demonstrations. Protests, 1975 - 1994 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Buddhism. Theological Education, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Buddhism. Unity. Schisms. Doctrinal Differences, 1968 - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Buddhism. Involvement in Secular Affairs and Politics, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Buddhism. Visual Materials, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Episcopalian Church Clergy. Ordination. Election. Retirement. Deaths, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Episcopalian Church. Conferences, 1980 - 1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Evangelical Church. General, 1975 - 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Evangelical Church-State Relations, 1973 - 1999 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Opening and Reopening of Evangelical Churches, 1975 - 1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Oppressive Practices Related to Evangelical Church Activities, 1972 - 2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Evangelical Church. Imprisonment, 1978 - 2001 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Evangelical Church Life, 1976 - 1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Evangelical Church. Preaching. Evangelism. Conversion, 1982 - 1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Evangelical Church. Defection from the Faith, 1996 - 1999 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Evangelical Church. Brotherhoods. Religious Groups, 1989 - 1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Evangelical Church. Charismatic Revival. Conversions, 1977 - 1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Evangelical Clergy and Priesthood. Ordination. Election. Retirement. Deaths, 1975 - 1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Evangelical Clergy, 1975 - 1990 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Evangelical Clergy Statistics, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Evangelical Church. International Relations, 1979 - 1989 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Evangelical Church. Western Reactions. Protests. Appeals. Aid, 1975 - 1999 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Evangelical Church. Public Demonstrations. Protests, 1976 - 2002 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Evangelical Church. Criticism by Believers, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Evangelical Church. Theological Education, 1987 - 1988 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Evangelical Church. Unity, 1981 - 1998 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Evangelical Church. Conferences, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Evangelical Church Architecture. Restoration, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Evangelical Church. Bible, 1973 - 1999 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Evangelical Church. Youth and Children, 1971 - 1975 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Judaism. Festivals and Anniversaries, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Mennonite Church. General, 1976 - 1978 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Mennonite Church-State Relations, 1975 - 1978 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Mennonite Church Life, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Mennonite Church. Western Reactions. Protests. Appeals. Aid, 1974 - 1981 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Islam. General, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Roman Catholic Church. General, 1968 - 1988 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Roman Catholic Church Administration, 1991 - 1993 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Roman Catholic Church-State Relations, 1975 - 2002 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Oppressive Practices Related to Religious Activity, 1972 - 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Physical Assault. Murder, 1975 - 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Trials, 1978 - 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Imprisonment and Exile, 1976 - 2001 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Affairs of Clergy. Hierarchy, 1973 - 2002 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Attacks in the Media, 1986 - 1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Roman Catholic Church Life, 1973 - 1999 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Canonization, 1976 - 1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Services. Rituals. Liturgy, 1985 - 1991 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Brotherhoods. Religious Groups, 1971 - 1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Revival. Charismatic Revival, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Excommunication, 1983 - 1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Monasticism. Nuns, 1981 - 2001 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Philanthropy, 1981 - 1993 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Roman Catholic Clergy, 1975 - 2001 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Roman Catholic Clergy and Priesthood. Ordination. Election. Retirement. Deaths, 1972 - 2001 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Working and Living Conditions of Clergy, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Roman Catholic Clergy. Statistics, 1976 - 1990 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Roman Catholic Church. International Relations, 1989 - 2000 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Western Reactions. Protests. Appeals. Aid, 1972 - 2000 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Public Demonstrations. Protests, 1976 - 2000 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Criticism by Believers, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Theological Education, 1972 - 1991 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Unity. Schisms. Doctrinal Differences, 1975 - 1987 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Conferences, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Arts. Architecture. Literature. Music, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Bible, 1988 - 1997 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Women, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Youth and Children, 1982 - 1993 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Roman Catholic Church. Visual Materials, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Quakers. Church-State Relations, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 31)